<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the Right Honourable Robert Earl and Viscount Yarmouth, Baron of Paston and Lord Lieutenant of the County of Norfolk by John Hildeyard.</title>
            <author>Hildeyard, John, b. 1662 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28072</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10347922</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10347922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1385:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the Right Honourable Robert Earl and Viscount Yarmouth, Baron of Paston and Lord Lieutenant of the County of Norfolk by John Hildeyard.</title>
                  <author>Hildeyard, John, b. 1662 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Roycroft for George Rose and Robert Clavel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Yarmouth, Robert Paston, --  Earl of, 1631-1683.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF THE Right Honourable ROBERT EARL and VISCOUNT Yarmouth, Baron of <hi>PASTON,</hi> and Lord Lieutenant of the County of <hi>NORFOLK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN HILDEYARD</hi> D.LL. Commiſſary of the Arch-Deaconry of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Cowſton</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Mors aequo pede pulſat Pauperum tabernas Regum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Turres. <bibl>
                  <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>George Roſe</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard in <hi>London.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:44930:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44930:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE The Truly Vertuous, and Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Pious Lady, THE LADY REBECCA COUNTES DOWAGER Yarmouth.</head>
            <p>The Author wiſheth all Proſperity on Earth, and Eternal Happineſs in Heaven: And in all Humility, as a Testimony of his Gratitude Dedicates this <hi>Sermon,</hi> owning himſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Her Honours Moſt Faithful and Ever Devoted Servant and Chaplain</hi> JOHN HILDEYARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:44930:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44930:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. IV. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And round about the Throne were four and twenty Seats, and upon the Seats I ſaw four and twenty Elders ſitting cloathed in white Rayment, and they had upon their Heads Crowns of Gold.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is our Chriſtian Priviledge that ſometimes we May, and when Spectacles of Mortality lye before us (as now) it is our Chriſtian Duty that we ſhould take a View of the Top of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor;</hi> even whilſt we dwell upon this our Native <hi>Calva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> mount up our Thoughts, and fix our Meditations on the Thrones in Heaven, whilſt we have our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations on Earth: 'Tis true, the Excellency, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Splendor of Heaven, no finite Brain, no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Underſtanding can poſſibly perceive or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend according to its full Proportion; for it is a Fruit of our Fall with <hi>Adam,</hi> and an Inſeparable Adjunct of this mortal and unglorified State here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, concerning things Coeleſtial, That what we know we know it but in part. Yet as a tender affectionate Father by giving of his Child a Glimps of ſome Rich and Orient Pearl, makes the Child big with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and Impatient for a full Sight thereof, and a graſping of it in his own Hand: So our Heavenly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44930:4"/>Father full of Compaſſion to the Sons of Men, though he detains from the Eye of our Senſe a full Comprehenſion of that Glorious State while we are in the body, yet now and then, he is pleaſed to give us a glimpſe, to let fall in his Word ſome Sparkles of it, that he may Inflame our Affections, and ſet our Faith on Tip-toes, that ſo we having the Eyes of our Souls within the Vail, in this Valley of Tears and Troubles, may always be refreſhed with the very Remembrance of thoſe Glories that are about His Throne. A Teleſcope is an Inſtrument of Man's Invention, that he may take a better View than his weak Eyes of themſelves can have, of thoſe ſplendid Lamps that ſo much beautifie the Cope of the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Heavens: Whereto the Apoſtle ſeems to allude, when he tells us that we can only behold the things placed above this Region of our Mortality, as through a Glaſs: Such a Glaſs, ſuch a Teleſcope, is this my Text, which gives a general Deſcription to us of that great and unexpreſſible Glory which the Saints have, who are glorified with God in Heaven. There were ſome indeed called <hi>Chiliacts,</hi> whom later days by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Name, have ſtiled <hi>Millinaries,</hi> who looking for a New Heaven on this Old Earth, would have theſe words underſtood of the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: But I could produce a Cloud of Witneſſes to make good his Words, who tells us it is not imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that any Company of Men, any Congregation of Saints, ſhould ever be found on Earth of ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt a Purity, and ſo exact Perfection as is here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44930:4"/>The words then muſt be underſtood of the Church Triumphant, as clearly appears from the 2d. <hi>ver.</hi> of this Chapter, which teſtifies, That the Throne about which the Seats of theſe Elders ſtood, was fixed not on Earth, but in Heaven. <hi>And round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Throne were four and twenty Seats,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, you ſee my Text is a true <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, on which our Souls in their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations may aſcend from Earth to Heaven.</p>
            <p>And in this Ladder I ſhall remark to you five moſt beautiful Rounds, or Staves, which in plainer Terms I would call the Parts of the Text. Firſt, The tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Excellency of thoſe Places in which the Saints were made Conſpicuous to St. <hi>John,</hi> 24 <hi>Seats.</hi> 2dly, The Tranſcendent Dignity of the Perſons upon thoſe Seats, <hi>they were Elders.</hi> 3dly Their Poſture, <hi>they were ſitting;</hi> the Saints of God were repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to St. <hi>John</hi> in the ſame poſture our Creed deſcribes the Bleſſed Jeſus, ſitting in Heaven, to expreſs their permanent, perpetual, and unalterable Reſt; they are at Quiet, they are at Eaſe, without Moleſtation, without Trouble, and that to all Eternity. 4. Their Veſture, <hi>clothed in White:</hi> Whence we note, that however Foul-mouths may beſpot it, yet White Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the fitteſt, moſt comely and ſignificant Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit for thoſe that wait at God's Altars, yea, for them too to be repreſented in, that ſit about his Throne. 5thly. Their Ornament; <hi>And they had upon their Heads Crowns of Gold.</hi> We in <hi>England</hi> borrowed our Proverb from the <hi>Latines,</hi> That <hi>The End Crowns the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44930:5"/>Work;</hi> give me leave here too to borrow from a Latine Author, the Obſervation, <hi>That a Crown ends my Text;</hi> importing that the greateſt Men, Kings on Earth, can have no greater Glory than to be Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; And Saints on Earth, ſhall have ſo much Glory as to be Kings in Heaven. And being met to Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Funeral of a Perſon, Great Indeed, Great in his Deſcent, Great in his Worth, Great in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Prince, and (what is beſt of all) Great in the Favour of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not doubt with all your Approbations to determine his Earthly Coronet is changed into an Heavenly Crown, and ſo the Text and the Occaſion will friendly conclude alike.</p>
            <p>From the firſt General of the Text, the Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Excellency of thoſe Places in which the Saints were made Conſpicuous to St. <hi>John,</hi> I muſt denote unto you Three eminent Circumſtances: Firſt, Their. Names, <hi>Seats.</hi> 2dly. Their Situation, <hi>Round about.</hi> 3dly. Their Number,<note place="margin">Their Names.</note>
               <hi>Twenty Four.</hi> Firſt, their Names, <hi>Seats;</hi> So indeed our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation renders it, and ſo the Vulgar, with reſpect, I preſume, to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing word <hi>Sitting:</hi> But <hi>Cornelius a Lapide, Beza, Complutenſis, Regius,</hi> with our own Learned <hi>Hamond,</hi> and a Multitude more, expreſs them by the Name of Thrones, according to the Original, and agreeable to the Title our Bleſſed Lord gives them, St. <hi>Matthew</hi> the 19th. where telling his Diſciples it is equally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a Camel to be ſqueezed through the Eye of a Needle, as for a Man whoſe Heart is ſwelled
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44930:5"/>with pride of, and enlarged with deſires after Riches, to enter in at the ſtraight Gate of Eternal Life. At which Doctrine whilſt the Diſciples ſtood mute and aſtoniſhed, St. <hi>Peter</hi> breaks ſilence, and ſaith, <hi>But we have forſaken all and followed thee, and what ſhall we have therefore?</hi> What Reward, what Compenſation ſhall be given us for this? To whom our Saviour makes Reply, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, that ye who have followed me in the Regeneration, when the Son of Man ſhall ſit in the Throne of his Glory, you alſo ſhall ſit upon Thrones.</hi> Oh the high Dignation of God! and oh the high Dignity of Man! Men are advanced to Thrones, and that with God in Heaven; what Imperial Majeſty like this? But to come cloſer, theſe Thrones or Seats were about the Throne, of whom? of the Bleſſed Jeſus certainly, who is ſtiled in the Book of Wiſdom Copartner with his Father in his Throne of Glory, and ſo is the Holy Ghoſt; the Glory of theſe three is equal, the Majeſty Coeternal, the Godhead all one and the ſame, and therefore, the Throne upon which they are here repreſented, is but one alſo. Well therefore was that Portion of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture choſen by our Church for the Epiſtle on <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Sunday,</hi> but of the three Chriſt is chiefly, ſay the moſt Orthodox Interpreters, intended in the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation; and therefore it follows in the 3<hi>d ver.</hi> That <hi>he which ſat on the Throne was to look upon like a Jaſper and a Sardine Stone, and there went a Rainbow round about the Throne, in ſight like unto an Emrald:</hi> The Rainbow fairly emblematizeth, the Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44930:6"/>which Chriſt wrought with God for Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the firſt, placed in the Clouds as a Sign of the Covenant of that Reconciliation: And it appeared here in ſight like unto an Emrald, more fully to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that Chriſt was meant, in whom, and from whom, we have our Spiritual Life. The Emrald be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a moſt comfortable Colour, and making all things look moſt freſh and lovely that are about it. And all Divines I have met with, have diſcerned the Face of Chriſts Divinity in the Green and Laſting Colour of the Jaſper, and the Face of his Humanity, in the Sardine-ſtone, which is of a Fleſhly hew and complection: All put together, ſhew that it is Chriſt's Throne that gives Denomination to the other; and his ſitting upon that Throne, that makes the Saints ſo Glorious. The other in the circumference, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their names and ſplendor from the Throne that ſtood in the Center, and that leads me to the ſecond Circumſtance in the firſt General of the Text, their ſituation round about.<note place="margin">Situation.</note> The Glorified Saints were made conſpicuous to St. <hi>John</hi> ſitting in Heaven, not in a ſquare nor angular, nor, as ſome contend it, in a ſemicircle, but in a compleat and exact Circle, which of all others, is the moſt perfect and moſt capacious Figure, well tranſlated in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Round about: Round about the Throne of Chriſt; from whom Beams of Glory are darted circumferentially, and their Angle of Incidence being ſtraight and directly level to the Angle of Reflection, the Glory muſt needs glance upon all: For Mathematicians tell us,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44930:6"/>that the Center is Perpendicular to every Point of the Circumference. Chriſt's Throne is repreſented here in the midſt of the other, as the Tabernacle of the Congregation the Symbol of God's Preſence amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſet forward in their March <hi>(Betoke Hama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanoth)</hi> in the midſt of the Camp. And the <hi>Pſalmiſt's</hi> ſaying, <hi>Promiſe unto the Lord and keep it all ye his Rounds,</hi> or all that are round about him, as we ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, hath Relation, ſay Interpreters, to that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camping of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs: And hereto it is thought alſo, our Saviour alludes, where he promiſeth, <hi>That when two or three are met together in his Name, he will be in the midſt of them.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Chriſt is in the midſt, theſe that are round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him muſt needs (like the Woman that touched the Hem of his Garment) draw Vertue from him. For as the Children's ſitting round about the Table, argues their mutual participation of their Father's Love; ſo the Saints ſitting round about the Throne of Chriſt, proves the Communication they have in their Saviours Glory, with which they ſhine above. <hi>Shine!</hi> Yes, and that with the ſame Glory that Chriſt himſelf ſhines withal. How, the ſame? Not by way of Reflection as the Stars borrow their Light of the Sun, but in their Meaſure, with the ſame Eſſential Beams: Otherwiſe the Saints would be ſo far from ſhining about Chriſt, that they muſt vaniſh, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear in his Preſence as the Stars do at the riſing of the Sun. Again, I cannot but obſerve, that this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt is communicated to the Saints glorified,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44930:7"/>in a due Proportion, but not in an equal Meaſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all; though they all ſurround the Throne, yet there is more than one Round about that Throne: There are higher and lower Rounds of Saints, as well as of Angels, in Heaven. Imagine ſeveral Veſſels of ſeveral ſcantlings caſt into the Ocean, of which ſome hold a Pint, ſome hold a Pottle, ſome hold a Gallon, they will all be filled, but yet a reſpect muſt be had unto each of their Capacities. Thus filled indeed are all the Saints in the Beatifical Viſion, but it is in the Apoſtles Phraſe according to the Meaſure of the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of which they are capable: And yet you believe, when both are in the Sea, it is as true Water that fills the Pint as that which fills the Pottle: No more is it a different Image which we ſtamp on a Penny from that, which is ſtamp'd on a Shilling, the Image of <hi>Caeſar</hi> is on both, and may be applyed by the meaneſt Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian to prove that there is a True community of the ſame Glory, but no Equality, which a good Biſhop once of this Dioceſs reports thus; <hi>In Heaven there is one Life, one Felicity of all, but divers Meaſures.</hi> Our Heaven begins here on Earth, and even here, varies in Degrees, one Chriſtian enjoys God above another, as his Grace his Faith is more. And Heaven will be ſtill like it ſelf, not another above from this beneath: He that improved five Talents was more recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, than he that improved but one, yet both reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Maſters Joy. And why ſhould we incur the check our Saviour gave to his Diſciples, asking, <hi>Who ſhall be greateſt in the Kingdom of God?</hi> Let us all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44930:7"/>ſtrive to get a Place about the Throne; What would we more than to be Happy? Though ſome may ſhine like the Sun, others like the Moon, others like the Stars, and one Star may differ from another Star in Glory, yet all about the Throne ſhall ſhine, and that for ever and ever: Nor, need any deſpair of Room in Heaven, of having a Seat about the Throne, though the Text mentioneth but <hi>four and twenty,</hi> the Third Particular or Circumſtance to be ſpoken to. Their Number <hi>twenty four:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Number.</note> This is a finite and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Number, put for an uncertain and infinite, which is moſt frequent in the Holy Scriptures, nor was there need of mentioning more Seats than El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Who theſe Elders were, and why no more, you will ſee by and by: <hi>In my Fathers Houſe,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>are many Manſions;</hi> Many, how many, Oh Bleſſed Jeſus? Nay, that no Tongue can tell, and therefore he expreſſeth them by a Word, indefinite, to ſhew that they are Infinite. Gods Hand unto his Children is not ſcant, like <hi>Iſaac's,</hi> he hath more Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in ſtore than one: For the Welcome, recorded by St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> is general to all, <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father, receive the Kingdom prepared for you;</hi> A King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom larg enough for all, no fear of ſtraightneſs there, where St. <hi>John</hi> whilſt yet in the Spirit, <hi>beheld and ſaw a great Multitude, which no man could number, of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Kindreds, and People, and Tongues;</hi> And of all theſe ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaved:</hi> And of this Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were the <hi>Elders</hi> in the Text moſt certainly; which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44930:8"/>naturally brings me to the Second General.</p>
            <p>The tranſcendent Dignity of the Perſons placed upon the Throne; <hi>They were Elders.</hi> But alas, their Number was ſmall, they were but <hi>twenty four,</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their <hi>Seats.</hi> I have read, <hi>That under this Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber St.</hi> Jerome <hi>underſtood the Jewiſh Diviſion of the Old Teſtament into twenty four Books:</hi> Others have thought here meant, <hi>The Diſtribution of the Sons of</hi> Aaron <hi>into twenty four Claſſes, by King</hi> David: Others ſay, <hi>That the Saints in Heaven, were repreſented here under the Form of the Governours in the earthly</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compoſed, as the Jews relate, of twenty four Rectors or Heads of the twenty four Quarters of High Streets of the City.</hi> But herein I willingly cloſe with <hi>Primaſius, That the Catholick Congregation of all Churches which iſſue from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting of Jews and Gentiles, when the whole Body, whereof Chriſt is Head, fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every Part ſupplyeth, ſhall have its Conſummation in Eternal Bliſs and Glory, is here ſet forth by the Twelve Patriarchs, the Founders of the Jewiſh, and the Twelve Apoſtles the Founders of the Chriſtian Church, in Robes of Purity, and with Crowns of Glory;</hi> They making up our number of <hi>twenty four,</hi> by whom principally, and chiefly, the Saints of the whole World were converted. And therefore being ſuch glorious Inſtruments, it hath pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to make them Repreſentatives of the Church, which Chriſt hath redeemed unto God by his Blood, out of <hi>every Kindred, and People, and Tongue, and Nation;</hi> and placed about his Throne of Glory. And now theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44930:8"/>Repreſentatives, are here ſtiled <hi>Elders,</hi> Firſt, Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, not in reſpect of Age, for there are no Gray Hairs in Heaven; the Soul waxeth not old when in the Body, much leſs when in its Glory: No Elders in the Reſurrection; Children that died in their Cradles, ſhall then ſtep over to Perfection of Age, and old decrepid Bodies, be reſtored unto Strength and Vigour, both made Perfect in the full meaſure of the Stature of Chriſt; Young or Old, Maim'd or Perfect whilſt in the Body, at the Reſurrection, we ſhall all ariſe in the vigorous and flouriſhing Age which Chriſt himſelf aroſe in, and that was about <hi>thirty three:</hi> We are told by ſome, <hi>That all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that have appeared under both Teſtaments, have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſuch an Age.</hi> And others ſay, that this our Saviour meant, in that ſaying of his, <hi>That in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, we ſhall be like the Angels of God.</hi> But ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and poſitively, they are ſtiled <hi>Elders</hi> in reſpect of their Dignity, to ſhew the Honourable and Venerable Eſtate of the Saints in Heaven. <hi>Elders</hi> is a Title of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and hath been in all Nations and Languages, given unto Men Eminent in Place, both in Church and State. <hi>Thus</hi> the Repreſentatives of the Majeſtick People in Old <hi>Rome,</hi> had the Name of <hi>Senators,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Elders. Thus</hi> the Judges of the great Jewiſh <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> were ſtiled <hi>(Zekenim) Elders.</hi> Nor doth that known Title of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> by which we dignifie the Governours of our Metropolitan Towns and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties bear any other ſignification, which in right Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography ſhould be <hi>Eldermen.</hi> Nay Biſhops, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44930:9"/>of the Chriſtian Church, are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the New Teſtament expreſſed by the Name of <hi>Elders</hi> too. But perhaps there is more than an Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Dignity aimed at in this Title of <hi>Elders</hi> when ever applyed to the Saints in Heaven, even to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate who they are that ſhall have a Place there, (viz.) <hi>Such as walk in the good old Ways, and maintain the good old Truths of the Prophets and Apoſtles.</hi> Without doubt that which in Religion is moſt Ancient, is moſt True, and Divine: Of whatſoever it may be ſaid, <hi>It was not ſo from the Beginning,</hi> may well be rejected for ſpurious and forged. It cannot be concluded to be from him that is the Ancient of Days, but from the ſpirit of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, who endeavours to make men change their Religion as they do their Faſhion, that he may plunge as many as he can in the ſame Damnation with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but for them who hold faſt the form of words received, who contend for the Faith anciently deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, who keep cloſe to the good old Path of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and Religion, My other three Generals in the Text do tell them, <hi>There are Seats about the Throne prepared, White Garments of Honour and Purity fitted and made ready, and Crowns of Gold held forth;</hi> to all which having ſpoken ſomething in the opening of the <hi>Text,</hi> I paſs them over, and ſhall now paſs on to a new, but ſadder Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is Comfortable and Glorious for a Chriſtian to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Joys of Heaven; but when it is remembred that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Entrance into them, he muſt twice put off the Old Man, once with its Luſts of the Fleſh, and afterwards with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44930:9"/>the Fleſh of Mortality, it is a putting Mirrh into his Wine; to remember that we muſt all lye down in the Duſt, and in the Diſhonour of the Grave, is a great allay to all Delight we have in the Expectation of the Glories above. But none can reverſe the Sentence, no Man can eſcape the Doom, Witneſs the Spectacle before us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Honourable Birth, and Ingenuous Education, if Wit and Learning, if Courage and Greatneſs, if Loyalty and Piety, if any thing could have given Immunity, have gone for a good Plea, have put in a Bar againſt a Sad Day, this ſad Scene of Sorrows had not been the Entertainment of this Aſſembly, nor we at this time with Sorrow in our Faces, met to Celebrate the Obſequies, who have ſo often met with Joy in our Countenances to welcom the Arrival amongſt us, of the</hi> Right Honourable <hi>ROBERT</hi> Earl and Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>YARMO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH</hi> Baron of <hi>PASTON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of whom to ſpeak fully and ſatisfactorily, is fitter for a Hiſtory than a Sermon. But though I cannot draw his Image in full Proportion, yet ſome Glimpſes I ſhall give you of his Vertues, that they may find a Place in your Memories, and live in your daily Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>It is expedient, nay expected, that ſomethings ſhould be ſaid, though all cannot. For my own part, he was pleaſed to give me ſo intimate Acquaintance with him, and that ſo filled me with juſt Arguments of his Praiſe, that I am more at a loſs to determine, what to leave out, than what to ſay. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin I would, but where ſhall I begin, or how ſhall I make an End? they ſeem alike difficult. But to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44930:10"/>my propoſed Method, I will begin with that from which he took his Beginning, <hi>his Deſcent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was Great in his <hi>Deſcent;</hi>
               <note place="margin">His Deſcent.</note> At this <hi>Quintilian</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth us to begin, when we commend to Poſterity the Memory of a Friend that's dead. And I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce many Authors that ſay that St. <hi>Luke</hi> begins here, when he ſpeaks the Praiſe of St. <hi>John Baptiſt:</hi> But this is the Work of an Herauld, not a Preacher, and the Eſcoucheons ſpeak enough, if I be ſilent. They ſpeak him a Branch of an Honourable Stock, a Gentleman of an Ancient Race, whoſe Family ever flouriſhed in the Firſt Rank of <hi>Norfolk</hi> Gentry, and is now admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Alliance with the Blood Royal: Whoſe Name came into <hi>England</hi> three Years after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt:<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> Collection of the Pedigree of the <hi>Paſton</hi> Family. Mss.</note> The Firſt of them was <hi>Wolſtanus Paſton,</hi> who was Buried at <hi>Backton,</hi> and after tranſlated with <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam de Glanvill</hi> his Couſin, to <hi>Bromhall</hi>-Abby, Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſaid <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Family was poſſeſſed of the Mannors of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> and <hi>Edingthorp,</hi> in the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d. In the Year 1314 there was a Grant to <hi>Clement Paſton</hi> to have a Chaplain in his Houſe, a thing very rarely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Authority, and without it, never.</p>
            <p>In the 8th. Year of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. <hi>William Paſton</hi> was made Judge of the Common Pleas, to whom the King granted as a ſpecial Mark of Favour 100 <hi>l.</hi> and 10 <hi>Marks</hi> a Year, with two Robes more than the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Fee of the Judges.</p>
            <p>This Judge married the Daughter and Heireſs of Sir <hi>Edmond Berry,</hi> by whom he had the Mannors of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44930:10"/>
               <hi>Oxnead</hi> and <hi>Marlingford,</hi> and divers other Lands in <hi>Norfolk. William Paſton</hi> Kt. the 8th. Son of the Judge, married <hi>Anne</hi> the Daughter of the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi> After this I find, Sir <hi>John Paſton</hi> by ſeveral Adventures there, atchieved great Reputation in <hi>France,</hi> and was choſen to be on the Kings Side in the Days of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th. at the great <hi>Turnament</hi> againſt the then Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> and others; and was ſent to conduct the Kings Siſter, when ſhe was to be married to <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why ſhould I name another Sir <hi>John Paſton</hi> who was appointed, amongſt others, to receive the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Catherine</hi> from <hi>Spain,</hi> afterwards married to King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. From which King there is a Letter of Thanks to be produced, to Sir <hi>William Paſton,</hi> for his Care in his Preſervation of the Emperors Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and other Matters of Courage and Proweſs.</p>
            <p>I will but name <hi>Clement,</hi> the Son of Sir <hi>John Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> who being Captain of a Ship in a War with <hi>France,</hi> brought the <hi>French</hi> Admiral <hi>St. Blaukert</hi> home with him, and kept him Priſoner at <hi>Caſtor,</hi> till he ranſomed himſelf with ſeven thouſand Crowns. He was Pentioner to four Kings and Queens, and in his declining Years, built <hi>Oxnead</hi>-Houſe, and lived in it till Fourſcore years Old: One of his Daughters was married to <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> Kt. of the Garter. This <hi>Clement</hi> was called by King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th his <hi>Champion;</hi> by the Protector in <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th's time, his <hi>Souldier;</hi> by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> her <hi>Seaman;</hi> and by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> her Father; And what need of more?</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:44930:11"/>
            <p>This minds me of the <hi>Father</hi> of our deceaſed <hi>Lord,</hi> who was a Kt. and Baronet, whoſe Fame both at Home and Abroad was as great as his Original, and who left in the Place he lived in, a freſh Memory of his great Parts, and Abilities, and laſting Monuments of his Travels and Foreign Acquaintance. His <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was the Lady <hi>Catherine Bertue,</hi> Daughter to the late Loyal, Valiant, and thrice Noble Earl of <hi>Lindſey,</hi> whoſe Renown ſhall flowriſh as long as our Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſhall remember us of <hi>Edg-hill</hi> Fight, where he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing General, valiantly fought, though with the loſs of his Life, the Battel of his Soveraign.</p>
            <p>No wonder then our <hi>Lord</hi> was ſo great, ſo eminent an Aſſertor of Majeſty and of the Religion in the Church of <hi>England</hi> as eſtabliſhed by the Law, as a late <hi>Dedication</hi> juſtly ſtiles him, when ſprang from ſuch Progenitors; From two Families mixt with the Noble Blood of many others, neither of which was ever ſullied with Faction or Rebellion, taunted with Error or Schiſm, or blackned with Irreligion or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm; and to a Mind inclined to Vertue, it avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much to be born well.</p>
            <p>The Place in which he was born was <hi>Oxnead;</hi> Lift up thy Head then, Oh Happy <hi>Oxnead;</hi> yea, grow Proud, and boaſt that it can be ſaid, <hi>This Good, this Great and Noble Lord was born in thee.</hi> More Reaſon haſt thou for thy Oſtentation in this, than any of the ſeven Cities had, which challenged and laid claim unto the Birth of <hi>Homer.</hi> But bar thy Gates againſt Men of Levelling Principles, who deny all Deference
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44930:11"/>and Honour to ſuch as this Lord in his Deſcent, whoſe Veins were filled in ſucceſſion of many Ages with Heroick and Generous Blood. The glorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of Honourable Parents are no ſmall Patrimony, and ought to be had in Reverence and Eſteem. But as for me, I muſt confeſs, I have much more delight, much more ſatisfaction in blazoning the Vertues of any Man than his Arms; I haſten therefore to the Greatneſs of his Worth, which ſhall be my ſecond General upon this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>He was Great in his Worth;<note place="margin">His Worth.</note> And here oh for the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Pencil of an <hi>Apelles,</hi> that I might be able to promiſe a Draught ſomething worthy the Original.</p>
            <p>The only Commendation of his Picture would be its Likeneſs to him; and this puts me in mind to ſay ſomething of his Face, which will be ever before me, which God had adorned with an exact Symme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Pleaſant Countenance, ſo that every Look was a Prevailing Argument to beget Love and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration in the Beholders. But the Cabinet is not ſo Beautiful as the Diamond that ſhines in its Boſom; And it will pleaſe me, and profit you moſt, to ſpeak of his Intellectual Worth, whereof I might mention as many Branches almoſt as I have Minutes left for the Remainder of my Diſcourſe. To avoid Prolixity what I can, I will reduce all to theſe; His <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> his <hi>Affability,</hi> his <hi>Learning,</hi> his <hi>Prudence,</hi> his <hi>Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Friendſhip towards Men</hi> was as general as his <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Friendſhip.</note> He was of a Nature ſo Kind, ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44930:12"/>Sweet, ſo Courting all; of a Diſpoſition ſo Prompt, ſo ready, ſo chearful in receiving all, that he had no Enemies except ſuch as deſerved no Friends. Where he placed Affection and allowed of Intimacy, his Friendſhip (let my Experience give its Grateful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony) was as firm, as immoveable as a Rock; It was not all the ſtarch'd Stratagems of Politick Heads, nor crafty Artifices of pretending Admirers, that could un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettle him to his Friend. He was very unapt, very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to hear Ill of thoſe, of whom himſelf had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Well. It was a Diſeaſe to him and made him Sick to have an Accuſation brought againſt any whom he had ſet his Love on; the Accuſer in thi kind always loſt himſelf, but our <hi>Good Lord</hi> kept his Friend: Nothing would make him deſert his Friend, unleſs it were his Friends deſerting him and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Sevice.</p>
            <p>For this he ſhak'd off many, or rather they ſhak'd off themſelves, and yet pretend to be as true Servants to the King as himſelf was, or he that ſpeaks; but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, they'l ſerve the King, as the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> ſay they ſerve God, not according to the Ancient Inſtitutions of Religion, but <hi>their own Way, according to their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi> So theſe pretend to ſerve the King, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Ancient Fundamental Laws of the Realm; and if they were let alone, they would, I fear me, do the Kings Buſineſs <hi>their own Way too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> His <hi>Converſation</hi> was always pleaſant, unaffected towards his Betters, familiar towards Inferiors, undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled towards any,<note place="margin">Aſſability.</note> and of eaſie Acceſs towards
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44930:12"/>all; and to none more freely than to the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whom he loved, whom he welcomed, and to whom he opened his Embraces al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, upon the very account they were ſuch. He gave Reſpect to the Loweſt, Honour to the higheſt; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways begging the Biſhops Bleſſing upon his Knee, That <hi>he would pray to God for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was of ſo great <hi>Comity</hi> and <hi>Civil <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanity,</hi> that as it is ſaid of him in the Comedian, <hi>Never any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Sad out of his Preſence, unleſs it was to depart;</hi> and as the ſame Comedian ſpeaks it too, <hi>None ever came at him, but they might learn ſomething from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Learning</hi> was very Comprehenſive, extending <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to whatſoever was worthy by a Gentleman to be known; nay, I muſt ſay, it was profound too,<note place="margin">Learning.</note> for he dived into the Bottom of whatſoever he ſet himſelf to enquire into. He was no Smatterer or ſuperficial Scioliſt, but had digeſted the whole <hi>Encyclopedy</hi> of Arts and Sciences, and was fully accompliſhed with all that from Studies at home or Travels abroad, could be expected in a Perſon of his Rank. He was, if not initiated, yet perfected in the Rudiments of Learning, under that moſt Eminently Learned, and fully Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Schole-Maſter Dr. <hi>Richard Busby,</hi> at St. <hi>Peters</hi> Colledge in <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and that Maſter hath often, and to this day will, (for as I take it, he yet lives, and long may he live to the Good of after Ages) tell how <hi>Pregnant this Young Plant was,</hi> and <hi>what great Hopes he gave of ſucceeding Fruit.</hi> From thence he went, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled his Name in <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:44930:13"/>where he heightned his Parts by ſuch Exerciſes as were ſuitable to his Quality, and perfected them by Converſation. And leaving there a Good Name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, he croſſ'd the Seas, and after ſome few Months ſpent in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> where he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved many Remarks of Favour from the King and Queen, he returned well skilled in the <hi>Lingua,</hi> and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with a keen and ſharpned Wit; with a Wit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Great, but Innocent; very Smart, but Harmleſs.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> were well imbeliſhed with quaint Stories, and witty Jeſts, and yet never did he ſpend his Jeſt to loſe his Friend; and, what is not uſually met with, though he was generally full of Diſcourſe, yet was he always inoffenſive, and never impertment.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Poetry</hi> he was very dextrous, and when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated any thing out of the <hi>Greek, Latin, French I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian,</hi> or other <hi>Poets,</hi> which he did frequently, it was hard to ſay whether the Author or he made the Senſe. And when any began any thing out of the Ancient or Modern <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> he ſeldom failed to go on and to tell what followed: So happy was he in his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, even to Admiration: Nay the common Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation failed in him, and he was a remarkable Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that General Rule, <hi>That a great Wit, and a good Memory, are ſeldom accompanied with a ſound Iudgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Wiſe ſettling Affairs in the County,</hi> muſt make his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Enemies</hi> confeſs he neither wanted Judgment nor Prudence,<note place="margin">Prudence.</note> nor Conduct; by which he reduced things to a much better Condition than he found them; brought many back unto their Loyalty, confirmed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44930:13"/>others in it; and when the Times looked grim upon him, ſtopt the Career, and put Spoaks into the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot-wheels of thoſe that drove <hi>Iehu</hi>-like towards a <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> And though in Popular Appearances, the Kings Friends and his with Tricks and Artifices have been outnumbred, yet he had Gold always to ſet againſt their Droſs, and with his Weight much outdid their Number in all Elections.</p>
            <p>But I am not willing, no not to mention our then Diviſions and Confuſions, when we ſeem'd all broke in Pieces, each fixing upon other Names of Reproach, even then by advancing the Kings Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, he gained the Affections of the Loyal Party, made them all his own, and at his death left the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them almoſt double to what he found them.</p>
            <p>Thus by <hi>his Prudent Management,</hi> he acquired great Fame to himſelf, great Peace to the County, and great Satisfaction to all Good and Honeſt Men. Nay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, even whether they would or no, he took poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many Hearts, to the Admiration of all that would not love him: Would not love him, did I ſay? Yes, 'tis true, ſome did not, they lov'd not him, that did not love the King, they lov'd not him that did not love the Church, and his Service to the King, and the Church, he valued more than he did their Love. Sure I am, they did not love him that vilified his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, leſſened his Parts, undervalued his Prudence, and reproached his Religion; That mercileſly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly, without colour of the Laws of Man, or Conſcience towards God, pierced the Sides of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44930:14"/>heartieſt Friends to give him a Wound, a Stab. When his Friends for his Sake muſt be taken into Cuſtody, and ſqueezed in an Arbitrary Skrew, or Hands as harſh and cruel: They perſecuted his Friends for his ſake, and with double Spight proſecuted him, becauſe he owned them for his Friends; but to proceed. When Men in great Place began to write after the Copy of Forty One, when Accuſations were invited, Calumny rewarded, nay, managed with great Art and Power, Then was this Noble Peer threatned with an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, <hi>Articles,</hi> as the Common Vogue went, were ready; and ſuch was the height of Malice, that <hi>his Friends</hi> were to be made, yea, forced to be <hi>Witneſſes againſt him.</hi> Then was he threatned with a Stone-doublet (as the ruder Language of <hi>Norfolk</hi> phras'd it, with Confinement in the Tower, as the finer Phraſe of <hi>London</hi> ſtiled it.) Yet, in all this, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw him daunted, his Countenance fall, or his Courage fail. He out-brayed his Enemies with his Innocence, and even then was more than uſually conſtant in the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> to teſtifie, that he was not by all the Noiſe they made, broke into any Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightment for Shame or Fear of what he had done.</p>
            <p>And when his Enemies,<note place="margin">5thly.</note> like <hi>Aeſop's</hi> Viper, had lick'd the File till their Tongues bled,<note place="margin">Magnanimity.</note> he remain'd invul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable. They accuſed him for going about to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Fundamental Laws and Liberties of the People, the way by which great <hi>Staſſord</hi> fell, and <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> who both, in their Stations, like this Noble Lord, ſupported nothing more: For the <hi>Rule</hi> is ſure,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44930:14"/>the <hi>Axiom</hi> infallible, <hi>To defend the Kings Prerogative is the beſt way to ſecure the Peoples Liberties, nay Lives.</hi> But then, ſuch is the blind Zeal of Malice, He muſt be impeach'd for <hi>Invading the Kings Prerogative,</hi> the Honour and Maintenance whereof was dearer to him than his Life. Nay themſelves had juſt before, made, <hi>his advancing it too High,</hi> his Crime. Their own Surmiſes were the Bills of Accuſation; but the Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of his Integrity to the King and Government, ſoon diſperſed all theſe Clouds, and ſet him in a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sphear, as we ſhall hear preſently.</p>
            <p>I have read that <hi>Hippaſus</hi> the <hi>Pythagorean,</hi> being asked after his Advance, what he had done, made Anſwer, <hi>I have done nothing yet, for no man envies me.</hi> They that do Great things, as this our Lord did, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape the Tongues and Teeth of Envy; but if Envy be the Accuſer, there is no defence for Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; if Calumnies muſt paſs for Evidence, the braveſt <hi>Heroes,</hi> the beſt Men in the World, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be the moſt reproached Perſons.</p>
            <p>Well! in deſpight of all they ſaid, and of all they did, this Magnanimous <hi>Heroe</hi> remain'd firm in his Worth, unblemiſhed in his Honour, and, what I muſt ſpeak to as my third General, unſhaken, and therefore Great in his Loyalty.</p>
            <p>Here I heartily wiſh that Speech he made, <hi>To juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie the Succeſſion of the Crown in its Lineal Deſcent,</hi> when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſo many were made againſt it, had paſſed the Preſs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it would loudly have proclaimed his <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> together.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44930:15"/>
            <p>His <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which he brought into the World with him, which he derived from his <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> Loyal Blood running in their Veins through all <hi>Succeſſions:</hi> This he improved in his Education, it being (to my knowledge) the great Endeavour of his forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Schoolmaſter, even in the worſt of Times, to plant Loyalty in the Hearts of the Youth under his Tuition and Care, where he found kind and apt Ground. This (his <hi>Loyalty</hi> I mean) he conſummated by his own Judgment and Approbation: he thought of nothing, he valued nothing that concern'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when the Kings Honour or Intereſt fell in his way.</p>
            <p>His Father yet alive, and his Domeſtick Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances very ſtreight, out of his Superfluities (ſhall I ſay) yea, Neceſſities, he ſupplied his Majeſty with Money whilſt in <hi>Exile;</hi> Nay, I had it from himſelf, <hi>That he borrowed to give, fearing his Soveraign might Want.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Father being dead, at his Firſt Step into Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Affairs, when he entred the <hi>Honourable Houſe of Commons,</hi> and took his place as <hi>Burgeſs</hi> for <hi>Riſing-Chaſe</hi> in this County, the Firſt Parliament after his Majeſties moſt Happy Reſtauration, he was the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he the Perſon, that moved and put to vote, <hi>A Supply proportionable to His Majeſties Great Neceſſities at that Time;</hi> upon which, that Parliament, to their Eternal Honour be it ſpoken, gave the King, <hi>Two Millions and an Half of Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:44930:15"/>
            <p>Sometime after this, he entertained the King, Queen, and Duke, and all their Nobles and Servants in Attendance, a Night in <hi>Oxnead-Houſe,</hi> where was prepared a moſt Sumptuous Supper, which coſt him three times more than Earls Daughters had hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto their Portions: Proviſions ſuperabundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Plentiful, and all Accommodations anſwerable. Thus, as it is ſaid <hi>Araunah</hi> did to <hi>David,</hi> did he as a King give unto the King. Nor can I omit to remark from his own Mouth, that the King had no ſooner put himſelf under his Roof, but he told this Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Baronet, <hi>That he was now Safe in the Houſe of his Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Tables being ſpread and Sideboards richly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with Plate, the King took Notice of ſome more Remarkable Pieces, which gave occaſion to Sr. <hi>Robert</hi> to tell him, <hi>That his Houſe was once better fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and he could have welcomed his Majeſty with greater Plenty of it, had not a Blew Ribbon that attended on his Majeſty with a White Staff, plunder'd it from his Father by Trunks full.</hi> Here the King diverted himſelf with a delightful View of the Houſe and its Situation, and what he found within: Left many Gracious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments of Kindneſs from his <hi>Hoſt,</hi> and next day took his Leave. But not long after, as an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Reward, his Majeſty by Letters Patents changed Sir <hi>Robert Paſton</hi> into <hi>Viſcount Yarmouth Baron of Paſton,</hi> the Ancient Seat of this Family; and ſo he quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him for what in a ſhort ſpace he put into his Hands, his own Vicegerency, and made him <hi>Lord
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44930:16"/>Lieutenant</hi> in this County of <hi>Norfolk:</hi> In the Conduct whereof his unuſual Diligence, and unexpected Zeal in Publick Affairs, begat Wonder and Admiration in moſt, and by his great Care and noble Deſigns for his Majeſtics Intereſt and Service, he ſoon made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf great and dear to the King his Maſter.</p>
            <p>I have often heard him tell with great Complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>The Free Acceſs he had unto his Majeſty upon all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions: What a Kind Ear his Majeſty gave unto all his Addreſſes.</hi> Proud of nothing, that ever I obſerved, but that great Truſt and Confidence his Majeſty placed in him. Proud! And well he might; for when all others frowned upon him, the King ſmiled, and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blickly Embraced him in the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> more than once, declaring, <hi>He had found him Truſty and Faithful:</hi> Nay, ſome that hear me, heard the King ſay, <hi>That whatſoever Service and Reſpects they ſhewed the Lord</hi> Yarmouth <hi>their Lord Lieutenant in this City, he took it done to himſelf,</hi> or to that purpoſe. In a word, ſuch was his Loyalty, he valued not his Eaſe, though his Body was unwieldy; he ſpared not his Coſt, tho' his Pocket did not overflow; he regarded not his Health, though for many years it hath not been much, when <hi>Publick Occaſions</hi> called him forth to <hi>his Princes Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whatever Wonder and Admiration all this had raiſed, it ſoon paſſed into the natural Daughters of <hi>Envy, Suſpicion,</hi> and <hi>Detraction;</hi> into the Spirit of <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy</hi> and <hi>Slander,</hi> and brought upon him great Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and many Troubles.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:44930:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Envy,</hi> that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke the Fire of <hi>Vetruvius</hi> broke out upon him, and might with the very Aſhes have buried an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, enclined and enſpirited him with the more real and greater Vigour.</p>
            <p>And now though his beſt Actions had an ill Name, and an ill Senſe put upon them by others, yet his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, who ſees as an Angel of God, made better Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of them, and as a further Teſtimony of his Royal Favour, gave him another Title yet more Honourable, and made him <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> and ſo reſtored him to that Fame and Reputation in which his firſt Procedures had inveſted him.</p>
            <p>And becauſe both the Daughters of <hi>Envy</hi> have blown upon it, I will be his Aſſertor, That great was his Love to the Ancient, Loyal, and Honourable Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration of <hi>Norwich,</hi> becauſe the Members of that Body (generally ſpeaking) loved the King.</p>
            <p>This one Qualification was enough to Entitle an Enemy to his Love: But I am ſure they found him their Friend, and manger the blaſts of Calumny, the New Charter ſhall remain a Token of it. I muſt ſay, he ſpared no Coſt, no Pains, as themſelves can witneſs, to make the World believe that he loved them. Moſt of the Tables in his Houſe have been often ſpread to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for their entertainment, and all his Friends em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to bid them welcome. Nay, his very Sleep, to my knowledge, was often broke to find out ways how beſt to ſerve them. And he commended the Care of the City with his laſt Breath to all his beſt Friends, and the Bleſſing of God, who takes care for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44930:17"/>as for their Lives; and by the Orders of his Providence confutes the Slanderer, that the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Juſt may be had in Everlaſting Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: Therefore the Mouths of <hi>Slanderers</hi> ſtopt, the Memory of our Lord ſhall be Embalmed in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; And ſo I am methodically almoſt at unawares brought to my laſt General, <hi>his Piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> He was great in the Favour of God, great was he in <hi>his Piety:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Piety.</note> Such was <hi>his Piety,</hi> that he always, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Buſineſs happened, opened and ſhut the Day with the ſame Key of Prayer in private unto God, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom miſt, whatever Company he had, Publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in his Chappel, where, without regard to his Eaſe of Body, or greatneſs of Quality, I never ſaw him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than Kneeling at Prayers, and Standing at Hymns, well knowing, that the firſt reſembles our Fall with <hi>Adam,</hi> and muſt be humble; the other puts us in mind of our Riſe with Chriſt, and ſo muſt be a Poſture of Praiſe and Thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>And what, in this profane Age, wherein Men ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neglect it, or if not, only take it to qualifie themſelves for ſome Place or Preferment, will hardly be believed, yet can be proved by many Witneſſes. What great ſtrictneſs he did uſe, what holy Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he did make when Sacrament days came, (and to him they never came too often:) He always ſequeſtred himſelf from all Buſineſs and Company a day before at the leaſt: And theſe were his own words, That <hi>he feared that Act of Parliament which deſigned ſo much good, would in time take away the Reverence due to that Holy
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44930:17"/>Ordinance, and make it a formal thing only to be done of Courſe:</hi> But it was not ſo with him, for as my inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions tell me, he received this Holy Communion as his <hi>Viaticum</hi> juſt before his <hi>Paſſover,</hi> not long before his death, with as much Comfort as Devotion.</p>
            <p>Had I not Been too long already, I would branch his <hi>Piety</hi> into as many Particulars as I did his <hi>Worth;</hi> But why ſhould I mention the Pariſh Church at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nead,</hi> where he lived, which he adorned and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? Why ſhould I ſpeak of the Chappel in the Houſe, which he built and conſecrated to the Service of God? Why ſhould I mind you of that Rich and Noble Plate he furniſhed God's Altar with? were I ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent they ſhould remain, as <hi>Jacobs</hi> Pillars, laſting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of his <hi>Piety,</hi> and to the Generations yet to come, the Stones out of the Walls ſhall ſpeak his Praiſe, as the Noble Fabrick of the Free School in <hi>North-wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> plentifully endowed, doth to this.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>weekly Lecture</hi> maintained there by the Bounty of his Anceſtors, hath tranſmitted the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their <hi>Piety</hi> down to us: Let the Tongues of the Poor, the Relief of the Widdow, the Succour he gave the Fatherleſs, the Clothing of the Naked ſpeak his Charity. Indeed he was made up of Pity and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-heartedneſs, of Chriſtian Kindneſs and Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>As to that <hi>Charity</hi> which implies <hi>Forgiveneſs of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> he was moſt Eminent: <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſſes</hi> at preſent made deep Impreſſions, gave ſudden wounds to his tender Heart, where all things were ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44930:18"/>contrary, but upon his recollecting of himſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were by miſtake or out of Malice, it was the ſame thing, or the ſame nothing in his Account or Memory.</p>
            <p>I told you how Tenacious his Memory was, but if it were to lay up an ill turn, it took no hold, but let that ſlip into Forgetfulneſs. After ſome (as I inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated) had ſet to work all their Engines, and like the <hi>Roman</hi> Retiaries ſpread their Nets to entangle him, whom otherwiſe they could not deſtroy: He often proteſted to me, <hi>Though he feared not their Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet he heartily forgave the Contrives.</hi> And when I ſaw him laſt, he repeated the Saving with this Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>So far he forgave them, that he had forgot the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</hi> And at his very Hour of Death, it ſeems, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>He was in perfect Peace and Love with all the World, and ſo was ready to reſign his Soul to God that gave it, his Life to God who had preſerved it with particular Marks of Favour and Providence;</hi> None of the leaſt whereof, was that wonderful Reſcue, which was effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him by no leſs than a Divine Hand, when on the ninth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> about eight years ago, a knot of Villains beſet him in the Night, ſhot five Bullets through the Coach, and one into his Body, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not Mortal: For which Deliverance he kept an Anniverſary Thankſgiving upon that day unto his death, and now keeps a Jubile with his Deliverer for evermore.</p>
            <p>But you'l ask, <hi>Had this good Lord no Faults? was he all Vertue, all Sweetneſs, all Goodneſs?</hi> I anſwer, He had
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44930:18"/>Infirmities, he was no Angel; yet let not that Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Sin, contracted in his younger time, of <hi>Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> be his Reproach, for he hath often bewailed it, and with abundance of Tears in his Sickneſs about four years ſince lamented it in himſelf, and ever ſince utterly abhorred it in all others: I have ſeen him ſhake his Head, ſit Uneaſie, and at laſt withdraw, when he hath heard ſome Young men extravagantly imbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, or rather imboſs their Diſcourſe like a Face with Carbunkles, with wicked and unprofitable Oaths. He did it more than once, when laſt amongſt us. He had his Failings, and indeed were it not for ſome Grains of allowance given, in what Pieces could there be weight? in none of Mortality, ſurely; but they are impure Flies that feed upon other Mens Sores; and they have too much Corruption in themſelves, that love to hear of the Corruption of others.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Faults, Frailties, Sins</hi> and <hi>Infirmities,</hi> ſo much by him bewailed, and through his True Repentance buried in the Grave of Chriſt, in whom was his <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> I doubt not but your Chriſtian Charity will think fit to bury with him in a deeper Grave, the Grave of Oblivion, whilſt his <hi>Vertues</hi> ſhall live and flouriſh, and find a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Monument in every one of your Hearts.</p>
            <p>And here now I beſpeak my Excuſe for not inſiſting much upon the great Affections he bore unto all his Relations: None underſtood Relations more, non obſerved them better. I left it to the laſt, becauſe my Inſtructions tell me, after he commended his Soul
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44930:19"/>to God in the Church her Prayers (which during his whole Sickneſs, he devoutly heard twice in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber every day) he gave Counſel, and adminiſtred Comfort to them about him, his dear Conſort, his beloved Children, his reſpected Servants, as if they had been the ſick and dying Perſons, and he the well and ſound.</p>
            <p>He received with great deſire the <hi>Abſolution</hi> of the Church, from the mouth of the Miniſter, who ſate up all night with him, and ſome few hours after: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight a Clock in the morning, fetching one ſingle Sob, he died, and ſweetly repoſed himſelf in the Boſom of the Bleſſed Jeſus.</p>
            <p>He died a <hi>Good Chriſtian</hi> as he had <hi>lived like a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> his own wiſh, and often repeated Expreſſion: He died a True, and Loyal Proteſtant, a ſound Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> he departed in her Faith, which they of <hi>Rome</hi> call <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and they of <hi>Geneva, Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Death was ſuch as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> uſed to wiſh for himſelf, an <hi>Euthanaſia,</hi> a Civil, Eaſie, and Well-Natur'd Death. Thus was he taken from our Eyes, in the ſame manner the <hi>Jews</hi> ſay <hi>Moſes</hi> was, <hi>by a Kiſs of Gods Mouth;</hi> A Death indeed, but Gentle and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene, without Trouble and Amazement, without Impatience and Temptation: And in the very Point of Death, he ſeemed to taſte of the Sweet of <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Peace,</hi> that Happy Reſt of the Life Above, where he ſits among them, <hi>That are about the Throne, clothed in White, with a Crown of Gold upon his Head:</hi> And
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44930:19"/>let it be our Care ſo to live, that every one of us may have a Place, within the <hi>Rounds</hi> there, to ſing <hi>Eternal Halelujahs to him that ſiteth upon the Throne;</hi> To whom, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, Three Perſons and One God, be all Bleſſing, and Honour, and Power, and Glory, for Ever and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Glory be to God on High!</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:44930:20"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT not being in may Power to keep this Sermon any longer from going abroad, I thought good to Advertiſe Thee, now thou haſt peruſed it, that there is nothing omitted nor added to what was: ſaid in the Pulpit: But having there not ſaid all that was in my Papers, I preſent thee with this <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> to ſhew thee, That the Five Corporations in the County of <hi>Norfolk</hi> as earneſtly ſtrove to have a Share in this moſt Noble Peer, as thoſe Cities intimated in the <hi>Sermon</hi> did to have a Right to the Birth of <hi>Homer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thetford.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt that called him Hers, was <hi>Thetford,</hi> who choſe him her Repreſentative in that Happy Convention. that brought in his Gracious Majeſty (whoſe Reign God grant may be Long and Proſperous) out of his almoſt Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years Exile; where this Honourable Lord then Sir <hi>Robert Paſton,</hi> offered up his Firſt Fruits of Loyalty, in putting it to Vote, (as I am credibly informed) <hi>What Day ſhould be ſet for his Sacred Majeſties Reſtauration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty being ſet upon the Throne, our Noble Earl ſerved in the ſucceeding Parliament for <hi>Riſing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Riſing.</note> where (as the Sermon tells thee) he put the Vote for two Millions and an half: For which he was celebrated in a Peotical Pamphlet, under the Character of <hi>Maximillian Paſton.</hi> The Honourable Houſe of Commons having that Bill,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44930:20"/>ſent it up by him to the Houſe of Lords, at whoſe Bar he preſented it to His Majeſties own Hand; and that Night received Thanks for it from the Kings own Mouth.</p>
            <p>Not many Years ſince, he made a Viſit to <hi>Kings-Linne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kings Linne.</note> where he was welcomed with a moſt extraordinary Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Magnificent Feaſt; and upon their Invitation given him, he honoured that Loyal Town, with taking up his Freedom amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yarmouth</hi> enjoyed him ſeveral Years their Lord High Steward, and gave him, when admitted,<note place="margin">Yarmouth.</note> a Reception an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that Character, and made him a very Noble Preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Norwich</hi> was as near in Service and Affection to his Perſon, as it ſtands in Situation to his Houſe,<note place="margin">Norwich.</note> took all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of manifeſting their High Eſteem of him, always gave him a Welcom in a Body when he came into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Four times choſe his Eldeſt Son <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Paſton</hi> (now Earl of <hi>Yarmouth</hi>) their Burgeſs in Parliament; and at laſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimouſly reſigned their Charter to their Moſt Gracious Soveraign, by the Hands of this Noble Lord and his Son; Whoſe Affections are as great to that City as his Fathers were. And in Memory of their many Obligations to his Father and himſelf, is pleaſed to own himſelf their preſent Recorder. It were but juſt here to tell thee, with what Courage this Young Gentleman in all thoſe Parliaments, oppoſed the then growing Faction, who, as it now appears, had then contrived a moſt Bloody Conſpiracy againſt the Sacred Life of our King and his Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, together with all that dar'd (when they were in the height of their Ruff) appear to be Loyal.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44930:21"/>
            <p>But being to give the Juſt Praiſe of the Dead, I ſhall only tell thee, that the whole County of <hi>Norfolk</hi> ſhewed at once the Value and Honour they had for this our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Lord, when in their Addreſs from <hi>Thetford</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes <hi>1682.</hi> to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, to Congratulate his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Return to Court; the whole Body of the Gentry ſubſcribed their Thanks for ſetting this Lord in Lieutenancy over them, owning the Happineſs of the County to the Prudent Management of this their Loyal Lord Lieutenant.</p>
            <p>Thus died our Noble Earl upon the <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>March 1682.</hi> who was born upon the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>May. 1631. As if Nature had eminently deſigned him to follow his Soveraign in all Future Services:</hi> Whoſe Birth was on the ſame Day in the Year preceeding. He lived moſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of all, and died by all moſt Lamented, and with great Appearance and Concourſe of all Degrees of Men, was Honourably Interred at <hi>Oxnead, WHERE GOD GIVE</hi> HIM <hi>A JOYFUL RESURRECTION.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page <hi>27.</hi> line <hi>3.</hi> for <hi>enclined</hi> read <hi>enlivened.</hi> The ſame Page line <hi>4.</hi> for <hi>real</hi> read <hi>zeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44930:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
